Finding Aid for Department of Postgraduate Medicine and Health Professions Education (University of Michigan) publications, 1928-1997
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Department of Postgraduate Medicine and Health Professions Education (University of Michigan) publications 1928-1997
University of Michigan. Department of Postgraduate Medicine and Health Professions Education.
0278 Bimu C41 2
Includes annual reports, bibliographies, bulletins, or course catalogs, directories, the journal Michigan Postgraduate Review, lectures, and schedules. Also contains publications from the Graduate Program of Medical and Biological Illustration.
1.5 linear feet
29 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Publications are received periodically from the unit (donor # 8226 ).
The Publications are open for research.
When the University of Michigan Medical School offered its first courses in the fall of 1850, the field of medical science was poised for a tremendous explosion of knowledge. Rapid advances in medicine and medical practices soon made the need for postgraduate medical education readily apparent. The University of Michigan Board of Regents acknowledged this need as early as 1878 when they authorized the faculty of the Medical School to admit medical graduates into undergraduate courses (Regent's Proceedings, January 22, 1878).
The admission of graduates into undergraduate courses was rescinded in 1892 when the Medical School began to offer graduate courses. A system of summer courses was instituted in 1902, which offered refresher courses and the introduction of new medical practices and procedures both for credit and non-credit. Despite these efforts there was growing demand for greater continuity and more academic direction of the program.
In January 1926, representatives of the University of Michigan Medical School, Detroit College of Medicine and Surgery (Wayne State University School of Medicine), and the Michigan State Medical Society met in Ann Arbor to consider ways of meeting the rapidly growing need for postgraduate study in Michigan. A committee was formed to study the problem and a recommendation was made for a program of postgraduate education to be assumed by the University of Michigan because of its state support.
The recommendation was placed before the Board of Regents, who voted on June 24, 1927, to establish a Department of Postgraduate Medicine within the Medical School. Dr. James D. Bruce was named the head of the new department. Although he did not receive any additional salary he was given an expense budget of $2,000 and office space in the administrative wing of the University Hospital.
The first postgraduate courses were offered from May 27 to June 24, 1929, at the Receiving Hospital, Herman Keifer Hospital, and Children's Hospital in Detroit. Twenty-four doctors registered for the course in internal medicine and twenty for the surgery course. In 1938/39, during the program's tenth year, fifteen short, intensive courses were presented throughout the state including several summer sessions. Total enrollment in these courses was 2,392, including practitioners from all over Michigan and several other states.
Increasing medical specialization helped to make the residency a vital component of postgraduate medicine. In 1927 when the department was founded there were only 270 hospitals nationwide offering a total of 1,699 residency openings. By 1945 the number had grown to 734 hospitals offering 8,930 residencies, and in 1976 there were 1,702 hospitals providing 65,046 residencies. (Graduate Medical Education: Proposals for the Eighties, Association of American Medical Colleges, 1980).
An influx of returning World War II servicemen resuming their medical education and specialty training triggered the development of the Decentralized Residency Training Program in October 1946. This program, also known as the Affiliated Hospital Program, was funded by a grant from the W.K. Kellogg Foundation and was designed to upgrade the quality of intern and resident (house officer) training in Michigan and to improve the distribution of physicians throughout the state. The program provided a link between the Medical School and other health education providers as hospitals in Detroit, Saginaw, Grand Rapids, Pontiac, Battle Creek, Kalamazoo, Lansing, Benton Harbor, Traverse City and Midland became affiliated with the University of Michigan.
On March 27, 1969, the Towsley Center for Continuing Medical Education was formally dedicated. The new facility, which replaced the inadequate space in the University Hospital, included the 518-seat Dow Auditorium and the 114-seat Sheldon Lecture Room. The addition of this facility greatly strengthened the delivery of intramural education and added a major audio-visual component to continuing medical education.
During the 1970/71 academic year the department underwent a major program review. The Ad Hoc Committee to Review the Department of Postgraduate Medicine, chaired by Dr. Chris Zarafonetis, issued several recommendations that resulted in significant expansion and restructuring of the department. The name of the department was officially changed to the Department of Postgraduate Medicine and Health Professions Education to reflect these new changes. The review committee also recommended that the teaching activities be expanded at affiliated community hospitals as well as in undergraduate medical student teaching and continuing education of allied health professionals. The recommendations further stressed the addition of research in the areas of teaching, learning, and evaluation of health services.
In 1977, as the department celebrated its fiftieth anniversary, the organizational structure consisted of five offices: Office of Educational Resources and Research, Office of Extramural Education, Office of Intramural Education, Office of Allied Health Education, and Office of Health Care Delivery Research. That year the department's programs reached nearly 7,000 physicians and medical students.
Grant-funded research components such as the Michigan Diabetes Research and Training Center were added to the departmental responsibilities, administered by the Office of Extramural Education. From 1984 to 1991 the department published the Michigan Postgraduate Review, promoting further outreach (The Medical Center Journal, 1964-1980, also carried postgraduate medicine news and articles).
The present structure is composed of three major offices or divisions (Office of Educational Resources and Research, Office of Extramural Education, and Office of Continuing Medical Education), with a three-fold mission of educational support, outreach, and continuing education underscored by research.
Chairmen of the Department of Postgraduate Medicine and Health Professions Education
1927-1942 James D. Bruce
1942-1954 Howard H. Cummings
1954-1967 John M. Sheldon
1967-1971 Harry A. Towsley
1971-1974 Neal Vanselow
1974-1980 William Harlan
1981-1982 Roland G. Hiss (Acting)
1982- Roland G. Hiss
_________________
Sources Consulted
Bruce, James D, "Postgraduate Education in Medicine," Journal of the Michigan State Medical Society, June 1937*
________, "Continuing Professional Education," Journal of the American Medical
Association 110, April 23, 1938*
________, "Postgraduate Medical Education," Journal of the Association of American Medical Colleges, May 1941*
Karr, Joan Mason, "The Department of Postgraduate Medicine: A History and Interpretation of its Development" (Ph.D. Dissertation, U of M), 1979
Kelly, Mabel F., "University of Michigan Department of Postgraduate Medicine," (unpublished history) ca. 1967*
Sheldon, John M, Thomas C. Flotte, and Mabel F. Kelly, "Postgraduate Medical Education at the University of Michigan Medical Center," Postgraduate Medicine 27, January 1960*
Towsley, Harry A., "University of Michigan Plan for Postgraduate Medical Education," Journal of the American Medical Association, 164 May 25, 1957*
________, "Remarks at Dedication of the Towsley Center for Continuing Medical ," Education," March 27, 1969*
Wilkinson, Charles F., Jr., "Hospitals' New Role as Michigan Decentralizes," Hospitals, February 1947*
________, "The General Practitioner," Journal of the American Medical Society 137, July 10, 1948*
________, "Michigan's Decentralized Resident Training Programs," Journal of the Michigan State Medical Society 47, September 1948*
Annual Report of the Department of Postgraduate Medicine and Health Professions Education, 1976-77 (Fiftieth Anniversary Issue)
"Postgrad Medicine," University Record, Vol. XIV, No. 1, October 1958*
* Copies of cited sources are located in Box 1 of the record collection.
The Department of Postgraduate Medicine and Health Professions Education Publications are divided into four series: Unit Publications, Sub-Unit Publications and Topical Publications, Chronological Brochures.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Dept. of Postgraduate Medicine and Health Professions Education.; University of Michigan. Graduate Program of Medical and Biological Illustration.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Postgraduate Medicine.; Obstetrics--Study and teaching (Graduate)--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Medicine--Study and teaching (Graduate)
Contributors:
University of Michigan. Graduate Program of Medical and Biological Illustration.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Postgraduate Medicine.
Genre Terms:
Annual reports.; Bibliographies.; Bulletins.; Directories.; Lectures.; Schedules (time plans)
- Unit Publications
  The Unit Publications series includes annual reports from 1972 to 1977 and a run of the directory Research and Service in Medical Education from 1983 through 1990, among other printed works. The bulk of the series consists of the course bulletins from the Department. This sub-series contains comprehensive announcements from 1928 through 1995, as well as bulletins from individual annual courses and teaching conferences such as Clinical Challenges of the 21st Century: The Annual Postgraduate Course in Obstetrics and Gynecology, and Advances in Internal Medicine. The series also contains the journal Michigan Postgraduate Review, which ran from 1984 through 1991, when it was discontinued for lack of funds.
  - Annual Reports
    - Annual Report, 1972-1977, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Bibliographies
    - Diseases of the Chest, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Bulletins
    - 1928-1995, 11 folders (Box 1)
    - Advances in Internal Medicine, 1972-1990 (Box 1)
    - Clinical Challenges of the 21st Century: The Annual Postgraduate Course in Obstetrics and Gynecology, 1990-1994 (Box 1)
    - Contemporary Issues in Obstetrics and Gynecology, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
    - Critical Clinical Issues in the Care of the Elderly, 1983-1985 (Box 1)
    - Modern Perinatal Problems, 1990-1992 (Box 1)
    - Northern Michigan Summer Conference, 1965-1986 (Box 1)
    - Pediatrics Meeting, 1949-1951 (Box 1)
    - Semi-Annual Extramural Course, 1941-1964, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Cookbooks (Box 1)
    - Hey Good Lookin’ Whatcha Got Cookin’?, 1976
  - Directories
    - Research and Service in Medical Education, 1983-1990, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Flyers 1947-1949 (Box 1)
  - Journals (Box 1)
    - Michigan Postgraduate Review, 1984-1991, 8 folders (Box 1)
  - Lectures
    - Michigan Postgraduate Series
      - A Course for Practitioners, 1935 vol.1 (Box 2)
    - Postgraduate Course in Ophthalmology and Oto-Laryngology, 1936 (Box 2)
  - Schedules 1929-1946 (Box 2)
- Sub-Unit Publications
  The Sub-Unit Publications series contains an accreditation application from the Graduate Program of Medical and Biological Illustration, catalogs of multimedia educational materials from the Media Library, and the handbook Guidelines for Obstetric Care from the Office of Continuing Medical Education.
  - Graduate Program of Medical and Biological Illustration
    - Reports (Box 2)
      - Application for Accreditation Self-Evaluation Report, 1989
  - Media Library
    - Catalogs
      - Catalog Supplement: Instructional Resources, 1982-1983 (Box 2)
      - Comprehensive Catalog, 1986 (Box 2)
      - Educational Medical Multimedia, 1978 (Box 2)
      - Instructional Resources: Video Cassette Slide/Tape Slide/Print, 1982 (Box 2)
      - Michigan Perinatal Education Program: Multimedia Education Materials, [1978] (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous 1978, undated (Box 2)
      - Multimedia Educational Materials: Media Library for Nurses, 1978 (Box 2)
    - Reports
      - Media Library Marketing Report, January 1979 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Comprehensive Coronary Care Project
    - Brochures undated (Box 2)
  - Office of Continuing Medical Education
    - Handbooks
      - Guidelines for Obstetric Care, undated (Box 2)
  - Office of Extramural Education
    - Directories
      - Affiliated Hospital Visiting Program: Faculty and Topic List, 1993 (Box 2)
  - Towsley Center for Continuing Medical Education
    - Dedication Ceremonies 1969 (Box 2)
- Topical Publications
  Under Topical Publications are programs from the Meeting of the Affiliated Hospitals and a publication containing the syllabus and readings from the 1977 Sibley W. Hoobler Symposium.
  - Conferences
    - Meeting of the Affiliated Hospitals
      - Programs 1966-1973 (Box 2)
    - The Role of Maternal and Child Health and Crippled Children’s Programs in Evolving Systems of Health Care
      - Proceedings 1970 (Box 2)
    - Sibley W. Hoobler Symposium
      - Syllabus and Readings 1977 (Box 2)
- Chronological Brochures
  Chronological Brochures consists of 29 binders containing brochures, course descriptions, flyers and publicity for continuing medical education offerings from 1930 to 1997. Note that volumes for 1968-1973 and 1985-1986 are missing.
  - 1930-1936 (Volume 1)
  - 1937-1948 (Volume 2)
  - 1949-1955 (Volume 3)
  - 1956-1958 (Volume 4)
  - 1959-1961 (Volume 5)
  - 1962-1963 (Volume 6)
  - 1964-1965 (Volume 7)
  - 1966-1967 (Volume 8)
  - 1974-1976 (Volume 9)
  - 1977 (Volume 10)
  - 1977-1978 (Volume 11)
  - 1979-1980 (Volume 12)
  - 1981 (Volume 13)
  - 1982, 2 volumes
    - 1982 (Volume 14)
    - 1982 (Volume 15)
      (continued)
  - 1983, 2 volumes
    - 1983 (Volume 16)
    - 1983 (Volume 17)
  - 1984 (Volume 18)
  - 1987-1988 (Volume 19)
  - 1989-1990 (Volume 20)
  - 1990-1991 (Volume 21)
  - 1992 (Volume 22)
  - 1993 (Volume 23)
  - 1994 (Volume 24)
  - 1995, 2 volumes
    - 1995 (Volume 25)
    - 1995 (Volume 26)
  - 1996 (Volume 27)
  - 1997, 2 volumes
    - 1997 (Volume 28)
    - 1997 (Volume 29)